<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="glossary"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="
		http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
		http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">
	<title>Glossary</title>
	<para>
		<table id="glossary-table">
			<title>Definitions of terms used within this manual</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="_1" colwidth="0.4*" align="left"/>
				<colspec colname="_2" colwidth="1.0*" align="left"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Term</entry>
						<entry>Definition</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Assertion</entry>
						<entry>A part of SAML message (an XML document) which provides facts about subject of the assertion
							(typically about the authenticated user). Assertions can contain information about authentication,
							associated attributes or authorization decisions.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Artifact</entry>
						<entry>Identifier which can be used to retrieve a complete SAML message from identity or service provider
							using a back-channel binding.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Binding</entry>
						<entry>Mechanism used to deliver SAML message. Bindings are divided to front-channel bindings which
							use web-browser of the user for message delivery (e.g. HTTP-POST or HTTP-Redirect) and back-channel bindings
							where identity provider and service provider communicate directly (e.g. using SOAP calls in Artifact binding).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Discovery</entry>
						<entry>Mechanism used to determine which identity provider should be used to authenticate user currently
							interacting with the service provider.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Metadata</entry>
						<entry>Document describing one or multiple identity and service providers. Metadata typically includes
							entity identifier, public keys, endpoint URLs, supported bindings and profiles, and other
							capabilities or requirements. Exchange of metadata between identity and service providers is
							typically the first step for establishment of federation.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Profile</entry>
						<entry>Standardized combination of protocols, assertions, bindings and processing instructions used to
							achieve a particular use-case such as single sign-on, single logout, discovery, artifact resolution.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Protocol</entry>
						<entry>Definition of format (schema) for SAML messages used to achieve particular functionality such as
							requesting authentication from IDP, performing single logout or requesting attributes from IDP.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Identity provider (IDP)</entry>
						<entry>Entity which knows how to authenticate users and provides information
						about their identity to service providers/relaying parties using federation protocols.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Service provider (SP)</entry>
						<entry>Your application which communicates with the identity provider in order to obtain information
							about the user it interacts with. User information such as authentication state and user attributes
							is provided in form of security assertions.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Single Sign-On (SSO)</entry>
						<entry>Process enabling access to multiple web sites without need to repeatedly present credentials necessary
						for authentication. Various federation protocols such as SAML, WS-Federation, OpenID or OAuth can be used to achieve
						SSO use-cases. Information such as means of authentication, user attributes, authorization decisions or security tokens are
						typically provided to the service provider as part of single sign-on.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Single Logout (SLO)</entry>
						<entry>Process terminating authenticated sessions at all resources which were accessed using single sign-on. Techniques
						such as redirecting user to each of the SSO participants or sending a logout SOAP messages are typically used.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>

	</para>
</chapter>
