<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="chapter-quick-start"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="
		http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
		http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">
	<title>Quick start guide</title>
	<para>
		This chapter will guide you through steps required to easily integrate Spring Security SAML Extension with
		ssocircle.com's IDP service using SAML 2.0 protocol.
		When done you will have a working example of Web SSO against a single Identity Provider. The steps will
		guide you through deployment of the <link linkend="chapter-sample-app">sample application</link>,
		configuration of IDP metadata (XML document describing how to connect to the IDP server using SAML 2.0
		protocol) and SP metadata (XML document describing
		your own service) and testing of web single sign-on and single logout.
	</para>
  <para>Public demo of the sample application is available at <ulink url="https://saml-federation.appspot.com">saml-federation.appspot.com</ulink></para>

	<section id="quick-start-prerequisites">
		<title>Pre-requisites</title>

		<para>Please make sure the following items are available before starting the installation:
			<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>Java 1.6+ SDK</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Apache Maven</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>SAML Extension relies on XML processing capabilities of JAXP. Some older versions of JRE might require updating of the embedded
		JAXP libraries. In case you encounter XML processing exceptions please create folder <emphasis>jdk/jre/lib/endorsed</emphasis> in your
		JDK installation and include files in <emphasis>lib/endorsed</emphasis> from the latest OpenSAML archive available at
		<ulink url="http://shibboleth.net/downloads/java-opensaml/">http://shibboleth.net/downloads/java-opensaml/</ulink>. The location of the
		endorsed folder may differ based on your application server or container.</para>
		<para>Due to US export limitations Java JDK comes with a limited set of cryptography capabilities. Usage of the SAML Extension might require 
		installation of the <ulink url="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html">Unlimited Strength Jurisdiction 
		Policy Files</ulink> which removes these limitations.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="quick-start-steps">
		<title>Installation steps</title>

	<section id="quick-start-download">
		<title>Downloading sample application</title>
		<para>Download the Spring SAML Extension either from <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-security-saml">sources</link> or
		from one of the <link xlink:href="http://repo.spring.io/list/release/org/springframework/security/extensions/spring-security-saml/">releases</link>.</para>
		<para>The Spring SAML Sample application is included in <emphasis>sample</emphasis> directory. We will be customizing
		content of the sample application in the following steps.</para>
	</section> 

		<section id="quick-start-idp-metadata">
			<title>Configuration of IDP metadata</title>
			<para>Modify file
				<emphasis>sample/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/securityContext.xml</emphasis>
				of the sample application and replace <emphasis>metadata</emphasis> bean as follows:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="metadata" class="org.springframework.security.saml.metadata.CachingMetadataManager">
	<constructor-arg>
		<list>
			<bean class="org.opensaml.saml2.metadata.provider.HTTPMetadataProvider">
				<constructor-arg>
					<value type="java.lang.String">http://idp.ssocircle.com/idp-meta.xml</value>
				</constructor-arg>
				<constructor-arg>
					<value type="int">5000</value>
				</constructor-arg>
				<property name="parserPool" ref="parserPool"/>
			</bean>
		</list>
	</constructor-arg>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>The settings tell system to download IDP metadata from the given URL with timeout of 5
				seconds. In production system metadata should be either stored as a local file or be downloaded
				from a source using SSL/TLS with configured trust or which provides digitally signed metadata.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="quick-start-sp-metadata">
			<title>Generation of SP metadata</title>
			<para>Modify file
				<emphasis>sample/src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/securityContext.xml</emphasis>
				of the sample application, replace <emphasis>metadataGeneratorFilter</emphasis> bean as follows and make sure to replace
				the entityId value with a string which is unique within the SSO Circle service (e.g. urn:test:yourname:yourcity):
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="metadataGeneratorFilter" class="org.springframework.security.saml.metadata.MetadataGeneratorFilter">
	<constructor-arg>
		<bean class="org.springframework.security.saml.metadata.MetadataGenerator">
			<property name="entityId" value="replaceWithUniqueIdentifier"/>
			<property name="extendedMetadata">
				<bean class="org.springframework.security.saml.metadata.ExtendedMetadata">
					<property name="signMetadata" value="false"/>
					<property name="idpDiscoveryEnabled" value="true"/>
				</bean>
			</property>
		</bean>
	</constructor-arg>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="quick-start-compilation">
			<title>Compilation</title>
			<para>
				When building from sources compile whole project and install artifacts into your local Maven repository using:
				<programlisting>gradlew build install</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				When using the release zip compile the sample application available in the <emphasis>sample</emphasis> directory using:
				<programlisting>mvn package</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can find the compiled war archive <emphasis>spring-security-saml2-sample.war</emphasis> in directory
				<emphasis>sample/build/libs/</emphasis> (gradle) or <emphasis>sample/target/</emphasis> (maven).
			</para>
			<para>
				Project files for your IDE can be created with <emphasis>gradlew eclipse</emphasis> or <emphasis>gradlew idea</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="quick-start-deploy">
			<title>Deployment</title>
			<para>You can start the application from the release <emphasis>sample</emphasis> directory using command: <programlisting>mvn tomcat7:run</programlisting></para>
			<para>Same can be achieved using gradle with: <programlisting>gradlew tomcatRun</programlisting></para>
			<para>After startup the Spring SAML sample application will be available at <emphasis>http://localhost:8080/spring-security-saml2-sample</emphasis></para>
			<para>Alternatively you can deploy the war archive to your application server or container.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="quick-start-sp-metadata-to-idp">
			<title>Uploading of SP metadata to the IDP</title>
			<para>Download current SP metadata: <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>Open web browser to the URL of the deployed application.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select <emphasis>Metadata information</emphasis>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select first item from category <emphasis>Service providers</emphasis>, e.g.
						<emphasis>
							http://localhost:8080/spring-security-saml2-sample/saml/metadata
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Copy content of the Metadata textarea to your clipboard.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist></para>
			<para>Upload SP metadata to the IDP: <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>Register yourself at www.ssocircle.com and login to the service.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select Metadata manager and click Add new Service Provider.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter <emphasis>entityId</emphasis> configured in <xref linkend="quick-start-sp-metadata"/> in the FQDN field.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Paste content of clipboard into the metadata information textarea.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Store metadata by pressing the Submit button.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Logout from the SSOCircle service.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist></para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="quick-start-testing">
		<title>Testing single sign-on and single logout</title>
		<para>Open the front page of your SP application, select <emphasis>http://idp.ssocircle.com</emphasis> IDP and press login. The system
		will generate a new authentication request using SAML 2.0 protocol, digitally sign it and send it to the IDP. After authentication at IDP
		with your account you will be redirected back to your application and automatically signed-in.</para>
		<para>Pressing local logout will destroy local session and logout the user. While a session is still active at the IDP an attempt to reauthenticate
		will proceed without need to enter credentials.</para>
		<para>Pressing global logout will destroy both local session and the session at IDP.</para>
		<para>You can test IDP initialized single sign-on with URL <emphasis>https://idp.ssocircle.com:443/sso/saml2/jsp/idpSSOInit.jsp?metaAlias=/ssocircle&amp;spEntityID=replaceWithUniqueIdentifier</emphasis>, after replacing
		the service provider identifier with the one configured as entityId in your securityContext.xml. It is possible to provide relayState data sent to your SP with parameter <emphasis>RelayState</emphasis>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
